The Cosmic Poachers

by Philip K. Dick

“What kind of ship is it?” Captain Shure demanded, staring fixedly at the viewscreen, his hands gripping the fine adjustment.

Navigator Nelson peered over his shoulder. “Wait a minute.” He swung the control camera over and snapped a photograph from the screen. The photograph disappeared down the message tube to the chart room. “Keep calm. We’ll get a determination from Barnes.”

“What are they doing here? What are they after? They must know the Sirius system is closed.”

“Notice the balloon sides.” Nelson traced the screen with his finger. “It’s a freighter. Look at the bulge. It’s a cargo carrier.”

“And while you’re looking, notice that.” Shure whirled the enlarger. The image of the ship bloated, expanding until it filled the screen. “See that row of projections?”

“So?”

“Heavy guns. Countersunk. For deep-space firing. It’s a freighter, but it’s also armed.”

“Pirates, maybe.”

“Maybe.” Shure toyed with the communications mike. “I’m tempted to put a call back to Terra.”

“Why?”

“This may be a scout.”

Nelson’s eyes flickered. “You think they’re in the process of sounding us out? But if there are more, why don’t our screens pick them up?”

“The rest may be out of range.”

“More than two light years? I have the screens up to maximum. And they’re the best screens available.”

The determination popped up the tube from the chart room, skidding out on the table. Shure broke it open and scanned it rapidly. He passed it to Nelson. “Here.”

The ship was Adharan design. First-class, from a recent freighter group. Barnes had noted in his own hand: “But not supposed to be armed. Must have added the cannon. Not standard equipment on Adharan freighters.”

“Then it’s not bait,” Shure murmured. “We can rule that out. What’s the story on Adhara? Why would an Adharan ship be in the Sirius system? Terra has closed this whole region off for years. They must know they can’t trade here.”

“No one knows much about Adharans. They participated in the All-galaxy Trade Conference, but that’s all.”

“What race are they?”

“Arachnid type. Typical of this area. Based on the Great Murzim Stem. They’re a variant of the Murzim original. They keep mostly to themselves. Complex social structure, very rigid patterns. Organic-state grouping.”

“You mean they’re insects.”

“I suppose. In the same sense we’re lemurs.”

Shure turned his attention back to the viewscreen. He reduced magnification, watching intently. The screen followed the Adharan ship automatically, maintaining a direct alignment with it.

The Adharan ship was heavy and black, awkward in comparison to the sleek Terran cruiser. It bulged like a well-fed worm, its somber sides swollen almost to a full sphere. An occasional guide light blinked on and off as the ship approached the outermost planet of the Sirius system. It moved slowly, cautiously, feeling its way along. It entered the orbit of the tenth planet and began maneuvering for descent. Brake jets burst on, flashing red. The bloated worm drifted down, lowering itself toward the surface of the planet.

blinked on and off as the ship approached the outermost planet of the Sirius system. It moved slowly, cautiously, feeling its way along. It entered the orbit of the tenth planet and began maneuvering for descent. Brake jets burst on, flashing red. The bloated worm drifted down, lowering itself toward the surface of the planet.

“That’s fine. They’ll be stationary. Good target for us.”

On the surface of the tenth planet the Adharan freighter lay resting, its jets dying into silence. A cloud of exhaust particles rose from it. The freighter had landed between two mountain ranges, on a barren waste of gray sand. The surface of the tenth planet was utterly barren. No life, atmosphere or water existed.

The planet was mostly rock, cold gray rock, with vast shadows and pits, a corroded sickly surface, hostile and bleak.

Abruptly the Adharan ship came to life. Hatches popped open. Tiny black dots rushed from the ship. The dots increased in number, a flood of specks pouring out of the freighter, scurrying across the sand. Some of them reached the mountains and disappeared among the craters and peaks. Others gained the far side, where they were lost in the long shadows.

“I’ll be damned,” Shure muttered. “It doesn’t make sense. What are they after? We’ve gone over these planets with a fine tooth comb. There’s nothing anyone would want, down there.”

“They may have different wants, or different methods.”

Shure stiffened. “Look. Their cars are coming back to the ship.”

The black dots had reappeared, emerging from the shadows and craters. They hurried back toward the mother worm, racing across the sand. The hatches opened. One by one the cars popped into the ship and disappeared. A few belated cars made their way to the ship and entered. The hatches clamped shut.

“What in hell could they have found?” Shure said.

Communications Officer Barnes entered the control room, craning his neck. “Still down there? Let me have a look. I’ve never seen an Adharan ship.”

On the surface of the planet the Adharan ship stirred. Suddenly it shuddered, quivering from stem to stern. It rose from the surface, gaining altitude rapidly. It headed for the ninth planet. For a time it circled the ninth planet, observing the pitted, eroded surface below. Empty basins of dried-up oceans stretched on like immense pie pans.

The Adharan ship selected one of the basins and settled down to a landing, blowing clouds of exhaust up into the sky.

“The same damn thing again,” Shure murmured.

Hatches opened. Black specks leaped out onto the surface and rushed off in all directions.

Shure’s jaw jutted out angrily. “We have to find out what they’re after. Look at them go! They know exactly what they’re doing.” He grabbed up the communication mike. Then he dropped it. “We can handle this alone. We won’t need Terra.”

“It’s armed, don’t forget.”

“We’ll catch it as it lands. They’re stopping at each planet in order. We’ll go all the way in to the fourth planet.” Shure moved rapidly, bringing the command chart into position. “When they land on the fourth planet we’ll be there waiting for them.”

“They may put up a fight.”

“Maybe. But we have to find out what they’re loading—and whatever it is, it belongs to us.”

The fourth planet of the Sirius system had an atmosphere, and some water. Shure landed his cruiser in the ruins of an ancient city, long deserted.

The Adharan freighter had not appeared. Shure scanned the sky and then raised the main hatch. He and Barnes and Nelson stepped outside cautiously, armed with heavy-duty Slem rifles. Behind them the hatch slammed back in place and the cruiser took off, soaring up into the sky.

They watched it go, standing together with their rifles ready. The air was cold and thin. They could feel it blowing around their pressure suits.

could feel it blowing around their pressure suits.

“Makes you realize we’re still Terrans, even though we’re light years from home,” Nelson said.

“Here’s the outline,” Shure said. “We can’t blast them. That’s out. We’re after their cargo. If we blast them we’ll blast the cargo along with them.”

“What’ll we use?”

“We’ll shoot a vapor cloud around them.”

“A vapor cloud? But—”

“Captain,” Nelson said, “we can’t use a vapor cloud. We won’t be able to get near them until the vapor has become inert.”

“There’s a wind. The vapor will dissipate very quickly. Anyhow, it’s all we can do. We’ll have to take the chance. As soon as the Adharan is sighted, we must be ready to open fire.”

“What if the cloud misses?”

“Then we’re in for a fight.” Shure studied the sky intently. “I think it’s coming. Let’s go.”

They hurried to a hill of piled up rocks, remains of columns and towers heaped in great mounds, mixed with debris and rubble.

“This will do.” Shure crouched down, his Slem rifle held tightly. “Here they come.”

The Adharan ship had appeared above them. It was preparing to land. Down it settled, its jets roaring, exhaust particles rising. With a crash it struck the ground, bouncing a little and finally coming to rest.

Shure gripped his phone. “Okay.”

Above them in the sky the cruiser appeared, sweeping down over the Adharan. From the cruiser a blue-white cloud shot, drilled out by pressure jets directly at the black Adharan ship. The cloud reached the parked freighter. It billowed around it, fusing into it.

The surface of the Adharan hull glowed briefly. It began to fall in, eaten away. Corroded. The Terran cruiser swept past, completing its run. It disappeared into the sky.

From the Adharan ship figures were emerging, jumping out onto the ground. The figures sprang in all directions, long-legged, leaping wildly around. Most of the figures hopped excitedly up onto their ship, dragging hoses and equipment, working frantically, disappearing into the vapor cloud.

“They’re spraying.”

More Adharans appeared, leaping frantically up and down, onto their ship, onto the ground, some this way, others in no particular direction at all.

“Like when you step on an ant hill,” Barnes muttered.

The hull of the Adharan ship was covered with clinging Adharans, spraying desperately, trying to halt the corrosive action of the vapor. Above them the Terran cruiser reappeared, entered a second run. It grew, swelling from a dot into a tear-shaped needle, flashing in the sunlight from Sirius. The freighter’s bank of guns jutted up desperately, trying to align themselves with the swiftly moving cruiser.

“Bomb close by,” Shure ordered into his phone. “But no direct hits. I want to save the cargo.”

The cruiser’s bomb racks opened. Two bombs fell, singing down in an expert arc. They straddled the inert freighter, bursting on both sides. Towering clouds of rock and debris rose up, billowing over the freighter. The black form shuddered, Adharans sliding off the hull onto the ground. The bank of guns fired a few futile blasts and the cruiser swept past and disappeared.

“They haven’t got a chance,” Nelson murmured. “They can’t leave the ground until they’ve got their hull sprayed.”

Most of the Adharans were beginning to flee from their ship, scattering onto the ground.

“It’s almost over,” Shure said. He got to his feet and stepped out from the ruins. “Let’s go.”

A white flare burst up from the Adharans, showering sparks in the sky. The Adharans milled aimlessly around, confused by the attack. The cloud of vapor had virtually dissipated. The flare was the conventional signal of capitulation. The cruiser was circling again, above the freighter, waiting for orders from Shure.

“Look at them,” Barnes said. “Insects, big as people.”

“Come on!” Shure said impatiently. “Let’s go. I’m anxious to see what’s inside.”

Nelson and Shure and Barnes gazed at it in revulsion. “Lord,” Barnes muttered. “So that’s what they’re like.”

The Adharan stood almost five feet tall, enclosed in a black chitin shell. It stood on four slender legs, two more weaving uncertainly half-way up its body. It wore a loose belt, holding its gun and equipment. Its eyes were complex, multi-lensed. Its mouth was a narrow slit at the base of its elongated skull. It had no ears.

Behind the Adharan commander a group of crew members stood uncertainly, some of them with weapon tubes partly raised. The Adharan commander made a series of sharp clicks with its mouth, waving its antennae. The other Adharans lowered their tubes.

“How is communication with this race possible?” Barnes asked Nelson.

Shure moved forward. “It doesn’t matter. We have nothing to say to them. They know they are illegally here. It’s the cargo we’re interested in.”

He pushed past the Adharan commander. The group of Adharans made way for him. He entered the ship, Nelson and Barnes following after him.

The interior of the Adharan ship reeked and dripped with slime. The passages were narrow and dark, like long tunnels. The floor was slippery underfoot. A few crew members scuttled around in the darkness, their claws and antennae waving nervously. Shure flashed his light down one of the corridors.

“This way. It looks like the main passage.”

The Adharan commander followed close behind them. Shure ignored him. Outside, the cruiser had landed nearby. Nelson could see Terran soldiers standing around on the surface.

Ahead of them a metal door closed off the corridor. Shure indicated the door, making an opening motion.

“Open it.”

The Adharan commander retreated, making no move to open the door. A few more Adharans scuttled up, all of them with weapon tubes.

“They may fight yet,” Nelson said calmly.

Shure raised his Slem rifle at the door. “I’ll have to blast it.”

The Adharans clicked excitedly. None of them approached the door.

“All right,” Shure said grimly. He fired. The door dissolved, smoking into ruins. It sank down, leaving an opening wide enough to pass through. The Adharans rushed around wildly, clicking to each other. More of them left the hull and poured into the ship, flocking around the three Terrans.

“Come on,” Shure said, stepping through the gaping hole. Nelson and Barnes followed him, Slem rifles ready.

The passage led down. The air was heavy and thick, and as they walked down the passage, Adharans pressed behind them.

“Get back.” Shure spun, his rifle up. The Adharans halted. “Stay back. Come on. Let’s go.”

The Terrans turned a corner. They were in the hold. Shure advanced cautiously, moving with care. Several Adharan guards stood with drawn weapon tubes.

“Get out of the way.” Shure waved his Slem rifle. Reluctantly, the guards moved aside. “Come on!”

The guards separated. Shure advanced.

And stopped, amazed.

Before them was the cargo of the ship. The hold was half-filled with carefully stacked orbs of milky fire, giant jewels like immense pearls. Thousands of them. As far back as they could see. Disappearing back into the recesses of the ship, endless stacks of them. All glowing with a soft radiance, an inner illumination that lit up the vast hold of the ship.

“Incredible!” Shure muttered.

“No wonder they were willing to slip in here without permission.” Barnes took a deep breath, his eyes wide. “I think I’d do the same. Look at them!”

They glanced at each other.

“I’ve never seen anything like it,” Shure said, dazed. The Adharan guards were watching them warily, their weapon tubes ready. Shure advanced toward the first row of jewels, stacked neatly with mathematical precision. “It doesn’t seem possible. Jewels piled up like— like a warehouse full of doorknobs.”

“They may have belonged to the Adharans at one time,” Nelson said thoughtfully. “Maybe they were stolen by the city-builders of the Sirius system. Now they’re getting them back.”

“Interesting,” Barnes said. “Might explain why the Adharans found them so easily. Perhaps charts or maps existed.”

Shure grunted. “In any case they’re ours, now. Everything in the Sirius system belongs to Terra. It’s all been signed, sealed and agreed on.”

“But if these were originally stolen from the Adharans—”

“They shouldn’t have agreed to the closed-system treaties. They have their own system. This belongs to Terra.” Shure reached up toward one of the jewels. “I wonder how it feels.”

“Careful, Captain. It may be radioactive.”

Shure touched one of the jewels.

The Adharans grabbed him, throwing him back. Shure struggled. An Adharan caught hold of his Slem rifle and twisted it out of his hands.

Barnes fired. A group of Adharans puffed out of existence.

Nelson was down on one knee, firing at the passage entrance. The passage was choked with Adharans. Some were firing back. Thin heat beams cut over Nelson’s head.

“They can’t get us,” Barnes gasped. “They’re afraid to fire. Because of the jewels.”

The Adharans were retreating into the passage, away from the hold. Those with weapons were being ordered back by the commander.

Shure snatched Nelson’s rifle and blasted a knot of Adharans into particles. The Adharans were closing the passage. They rolled heavy emergency plates into position and welded them rapidly into place.

“Burn a hole,” Shure barked. He turned his gun on the wall of the ship. “They’re trying to seal us in here.”

Barnes turned his gun on the wall. The two Slem beams ate into the side of the ship. Abruptly the wall gave way, a circular hole falling out.

Outside the ship Terran soldiers were fighting with the Adharans. The Adharans were retreating, making their way back as best they could, firing and hopping. Some of them hopped up onto their ship. Others turned and fled, throwing their guns down. They milled about in helpless confusion, running and leaping in all directions, clicking wildly.

The parked cruiser glowed into life, its heavy guns lowering into position.

“Don’t fire,” Shure ordered through his phone. “Leave their ship alone. It isn’t necessary.”

“They’re finished,” Nelson gasped, jumping onto the ground. Shure and Barnes leaped after him, out of the Adharan ship onto the surface. “They don’t have a chance. They don’t know how to fight.”

Shure waved a group of Terran soldiers over to him. “Over here! Hurry up, damn it.”

Milky jewels were spilling out of the ship onto the ground, rolling and bouncing through the hole. Part of the containing struts had been blasted away. Stacks of jewels cascaded down and rolled around their feet, getting in their way.

Barnes scooped one up. It burned his gloved hand faintly, tingling his fingers. He held it to the light. The globe was opaque. Vague shapes swam in the milky fire, drifting back and forth. The globe pulsed and glowed, as if it were alive.

Nelson grinned at him. “Really something, isn’t it?”

“Lovely.” Barnes picked up another. On the hull of the ship an Adharan fired down at him futilely. “Look at them all. There must be thousands of them.”

Most of the fighting had ceased. The remaining Adharans were being rounded up by the Terran soldiers.

“What about them?” Nelson said.

Shure didn’t answer. He was examining one of the jewels, turning it over and over. “Look at it,” he murmured. “Brings out different colors each way you hold it. Did you ever see anything like it?”

The big Terran freighter bumped to a landing. Its loading hatches dropped down. Jitney cars rumbled out, a fleet of stubby trucks. The jitney cars crossed to the Adharan ship. Ramps dropped into place, as robot scoops prepared to go to work.

“Shovel them up,” Silvanus Fry rambled, crossing over to Captain Shure. The Manager of Terran Enterprises wiped his forehead with a red handkerchief. “Astonishing haul, Captain. Quite a find.” He put out his moist palm and they shook.

“I can’t understand how we could have missed them,” Shure said. “The Adharans walked in and picked them up. We watched them going from one planet to the next, like some sort of honey bee. I don’t know why our own teams didn’t find them.”

Fry shrugged. “What does it matter?” He examined one of the jewels, tossing it up in the air and catching it. “I imagine every woman on Terra will have one of these around her neck— or will want one of these around her neck. In six months they won’t know how they ever lived without them. That’s the way people are, Captain.” He put the globe into his briefcase, snapping it shut. “I think I’ll take one home to my own wife.”

The Adharan commander was brought over by a Terran soldier. He was silent, clicking nothing. The surviving Adharans had been stripped of their weapons and allowed to resume work on their ship. They had got the hull patched and most of the corrosion repaired.

“We’re letting you go,” Shure said to the Adharan commander. “We could try you as pirates and shoot you, but there wouldn’t be much point in it. Better tell your government to stay out of the Sirius system from now on.”

“He can’t understand you,” Barnes said mildly.

“I know. This is a formality. He gets the general idea, though.”

The Adharan commander stood silently, waiting.

“That’s all.” Shure waved impatiently toward the Adharan ship. “Go on. Take off. Clear out of here. And don’t come back.”

The soldier released the Adharan. The Adharan made his way slowly back to his ship. He disappeared through the hatch. The Adharans working on the hull of the ship gathered up their equipment and followed their commander inside.

The hatches closed. The Adharan ship shuddered, as its jets roared into life. Awkwardly it lifted from the surface, rising up into the sky. It turned, heading toward outer space.

Shure watched it until it was gone.

“That’s that.” He and Fry walked rapidly toward the cruiser. “You think these jewels will attract some attention on Terra?”

“Of course. Is there any doubt?”

“No.” Shure was deep in thought. “They got to only five of the ten planets. There should be more on the remaining inner planets. After this load gets back to Terra we can begin work on the inner planets. If the Adharans found them we should be able to.”

Fry’s eyes glittered behind his glasses. “Fine. I didn’t realize there would be more.”

“There are.” Shure frowned, rubbing his jaw. “At least, there ought to be.”

“What’s wrong?”

“I can’t understand why we never found them.”

Fry clapped him on the back. “Don’t worry!”

The Adharan commander sat at his control screen, adjusting his communication circuits.

The Check Base on the second planet of the Adharan system came into focus. The commander raised the sound cone to his neck.

“Bad luck.”

“What occurred?”

“Terrans attacked us and seized the balance of our cargo.”

“How much was still aboard?”

“Half. We had been to only five of the planets.”

“That’s unfortunate. They took the load to Terra?”

“I presume.”

Silence for a time. “How warm is Terra?”

“Fairly warm, I understand.”

“Maybe it will work out all right. We didn’t contemplate any hatching on Terra, but if—”

“I don’t like the idea of Terrans having a good part of our next generation. I’m sorry we hadn’t gotten farther in the distribution.”

“Don’t worry. We’ll petition the Mother to lay a whole new group to make up for it.”

“But what would the Terrans want with our eggs? Nothing but trouble will come, when hatching begins. I can’t understand them. Terran minds are beyond comprehension. I shudder to think what it will be like when the eggs hatch. — And on a humid planet, hatching should begin fairly soon...”

Notes

Philip K. Dick The Cosmic Poachers (“Burglar”) 10/22/52. Imagination, July 1953.